

# Mazen Zayat

Linkedin Profile: <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/pub/mazen-zayat/1a/857/308">http://www.linkedin.com/pub/mazen-zayat/1a/857/308</a>

### **CONTACT INFO**

mazen.zayat@me.com /email
Syrian /nationality
Malmo, Sweden /current city, residency
+46 73-7890409 /SE mobile, Face Time

#### **SKILLS**

- Reliable common sense.
- Analytical thinker and quick learner
- Ability to operate in full autonomy and handle responsibilities.
- Focused on finding middle ground.
- Change catalyst in organization & self
- Effective communicator with wide range of **people** types (backgrounds, ages & objectives)

### **EDUCATION**

- Jun 2010:Oxford Leadership development programme, team in charge of "facilitate the creation and growth for strategic industries" a program by University of Oxford -Said business school
- Aug 2007: MBA from HIBA "Higher Institute of Business Administration", major of finance and financial markets from DAUPHINE university-Paris
- Jun 2005: Bachelor of Sciences in applied chemistry from Damascus University- Faculty of sciences

## **PROFILE**

Sharp personality, organized mindset with ability to evaluate and adapt according to bigger picture vision.

10+ years experiance in customer management, business development, commercial operations and portfolio deployment with leading local and multinational companies. Covering greater Middle East (MENA, GCC, Turkey & Iran) and Sub-Sahara Africa.

Excel in long term planning and continuous development. Relocated recently to Sweden and keen for the upcoming challenge!

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Tetra Pak 2008- Mar 2015 World leader in processing and aseptic filling technologies, established in more than 156 countries with 21,000+ employees

<u>Key Account Manager</u> 2012-2015 In charge of managing Syria in addition to selected customers' affairs in: Iraq, Jordan, Lebanon, UAE & SA

- Successfully managed challenging transition relationship involving overlapping multinationals and complex brand ownership matrix.
- Maintain customers relation & operation immune from crises, embargo and dramatic change in business environment.

Account Manager

Key Account Executive

In Charge of managing customers and leading business development in terms of: vision & execution

- Pitched, negotiated and sealed deals of 10+ Mio USD value each.
- Reached agreement with government toward establishing joint program both on business and social development scale.
- 38% reduction in credit days with existing customers.

Other roles & positions in parallel to commercial duties:

- Country spokes person for media & government
- · Customer system cost module champion
- Portfolio deployment champion

<u>Cluster Process Driver /GME&A/</u> 2014-Mar 2015 In charge of implementing Value Selling among all countries from Iran east to Morocco west down to South Africa:

- Strategy alignment & action plan with global team.
- · Building cluster team and related competence mapping.

Appreciation from both customers and colleagues led to Tetra Pak recognition as a high potential employee.

# **LANGUAGES**

• Fluent in: English & Arabic

• Swedish: in the pipeline

## **TRAINING**

- Value selling: Lund 2015 / Dubai 2014
- Procurement Understanding & Negotiation: Dubai 2014
- Portfolio management: 2010/11/12/13
- Media crises management: 2010/11/12
- Advanced presentation skills 2012/14
- Leading others: 2013
- Moral Foundation of politics: Yale University /Coursera

## OTHER JOBS HIGHLIGHTS

- Mar 2007-Dec 2007: Duty Manager / SHERATON Damascus Hotel & Tower
  - Represent Hotel management during off-working hours
  - Drive "Guest Satisfaction Index"
- 2003-2006 Formula Chemical Services (entrepreneurial project to produce special detergents for HORICA sector.

Open for International **relocation** and/or travel

SyrChem 2005- Dec 2007 Regional representative and agent for chemical & pharmaceutical ingredient, flavoring and food coloring- Syria

**Business Development Manager** 

In charge of analyzing, projecting and negotiating new products to market via:

- Framing new product introduction parameters process
- Designing annual commercial strategy for launching new products including stock planning, pricing and distribution

Damas Investments 2003-Jun 2005
Brokerage house for trading in global markets & platforms - Syria

# **Operation Manager**

In charge of managing day to day activities of the trading room and its employees including:

- Handling customers activities, manage financial relationship
- · Representing the company in relevant events

# OTHER EXPERIENCES: PREPARED STUDIES

On add-hock bases, the following business studies prepared:

- BAGs Holding /investment & construction group-Austria/: Internship -Market study for cement plant in Syria-
- <u>assalygroup.com</u> /Bank relationship management/: Kick off operation study including feasibility study, market potential and pricing strategy
- SyrChem / importing & investment company / feasibility for importing cement to Syrian market
- <u>samma3a.com</u> /headphones review and online shop/: company strategy & website launching.

# **INTEREST & VOLUNTEERING**

Active member in several civil society bodies:

- British Syrian Society: Platinum member
- Bidaya NGO: Mentor /micro financing & coaching /
- Syrian American Council : Active member

Keen interests: ME politics & Geopolitics, crowd funding, Apps development & new technologies.

Sports: Darts & Tennis

Mazen Zayat